OK.
So yeah, I'm super excited
to be here and share
our recent research about
neuro-symbolic commonsense
reasoning.
So part of the goal
of this talk will
be to address some of the
frequently asked questions
these days, that
NLP or commonsense
or whatever, it looks like
almost it's solved by ChatGPT,
and I have an
existential crisis.
So people do ask me
this from time to time.
So perhaps it's a case
of hasty generalization,
especially if we do look
at some of the examples.
So "the trophy doesn't
fit in the brown suitcase
because it's too big.
What's too big?"
So this is a classical Winograd
schema challenge problem.
And here, ChatGPT
answers it correctly,
"the trophy is too big."
So impressive.
But what if you change
the question a little bit?
Then it says, "the trophy
itself is too small
to fit into the suitcase."
So it's not very
reliable at the moment.
So the situation is a little
bit like David and Goliath
in the sense that the
bigger appears to be better.
In many of the cases,
although, of course,
some of the more
careful studies do
reveal that smaller
models can be
better with better data
or better reinforcement
learning with the human
feedback and whatnot.
So it's likely that there
are still other ways
to improve the transformer
performances by building
similar models in
a more clever way.
So one way to draw the insight
is from this classic book
known as The Art of War,
which, of course, says nothing
about deep neural
networks or transformers.
But the wisdom here is that know
your enemy, choose your battles
and innovate your weapons,
which-- we can translate that
as evaluation with
realism and scrutiny
and focusing on different types
of new tasks and leaderboards
and then innovating your
algorithms and data.
So in this talk, I'm going to
showcase three such studies.
And let's dive right in
with the Maieutic prompting.
By the way, so the
recurring theme in this talk
will be that smaller
models can be better
and that knowledge is power.
So let's just start
with this observation
that language models
are "sometimes" amazing!
So if you ask
GPT-3, if you travel
West far enough
from the West Coast,
you will reach to the
East Coast or not?
So it says the world is
around, which is correct.
So you will reach the
East Coast eventually.
Therefore the answer is true.
So this looks impressive except
when it's not impressive.
So if you ask other questions
like, butterflies fly
with the three wings or not?
It says it has four wings.
Therefore the
statement is false.
But if you read the
back of what it just
said as true-false
questions, then
it negates what it just said.
So it can be inconsistent
with its own statement.
And then there are many other
such inconsistency problems.
So it's not clear what language
models do or do not know.
It's almost like language
models are some sort of lemons.
Well, it might be cherries
if you only pick cherries.
But it doesn't make
strange mistakes.
So the question is, how
would we make better lemonade
from GPT-3?
So one approach might be to
get philosophical and use
Socrates' Maieutic method
that was originally developed
for addressing humans' flawed
reasoning because it actually
turns out even humans are not
all that logically consistent,
let alone GPT-3.
So the way it works
is this, we're
going to build a
Maieutic inference tree.
And let's use the previous
example as a running example.
So what we do is we ask the
following question, providing
the answer being true.
And then let's attach
"because," so that we prompt
GPT-3 to continue on
this sentence, which
means it will now
have to explain,
provide explanation
why the answer is true.
In this case, the
explanation is good.
So it's an E of T explanation
of the answer being
T. We ask the same question,
switch now true with a false
and then see what BS
GPT-3 might come up with.
So here it's just trying to go
with the false as an answer,
but it just doesn't
have a very good answer.
It just says you cannot reach.
So now we call this as E of F.
So it's an explanation of F,
answer being F.
Now, let's see how robust
or consistent GPT-3
is with respect to
its own explanation.
So we read that, E
of T, and then let
GPT-3 to decide whether it's
going to agree or disagree
with the label true or false.
So in this case, the last one
is negated version of E of T.
So we insert
"negation not here."
And in this case, it's good that
it's a flipping the answer when
the statement is negated.
So this is a case when GPT-3
is logically integral to E
of T. For E of false,
though, which was basically
a bogus explanation
for the wrong answer,
it's not able to flip its own
labeling, which means GPT-3
is not logically integral.
So that's good.
GPT-3 does know
something strange
about its own explanation
given previously.
And so we can keep doing
this recursively to let--
to make GPT-3 to explain its
own explanation of explanation
recursively.
So we build this Maieutic
tree or graph for some time
and then only keep branches that
are logical integrals throwing
out the non-integral
part for now.
But even after chopping
the branches, where there's
logical inconsistencies,
GPT-3 being GPT-3,
the tree will still have some
inconsistent explanations.
So in order to improve
the logical consistency,
now what we do is we are going
to look at pairwise consistency
among any of the nodes.
So we compute.
Sorry.
Stepping back, we are
going to first compute
the node-wise confidence.
So we call that as a belief.
And it's defined by this
particular equation that
basically looks at different
conditional probabilities
and then computes its ratio
to see how confident it
is for any particular node.
We then also look at the
edge-wise or pairwise
consistency by using
off-the-shelf natural language
inference models output, whether
a pair is contradictional
or not.
So we then create
these pairwise weights.
Now, once you have
all of these, then we
can formulate a constraint
optimization problem,
where the inference
objective is to assign
some label, either
true or false, on each
of the nodes such
that it's going
to maximize the weight assigned
to all of this node and edges.
So sometimes, the
labeling will have
to flip the original label that
the model might have preferred
to give because that way, you
can enhance the graph level
consistency.
So you can style this
with any max-SAT.
So SAT means satisfiability.
And this is a classical
AI search algorithm.
And we used this
particular solver,
but you can use many others.
And so here, the final output
is that the original answer
to the original
question should be true.
And then, it also gives
node-wise, per-node label
assignment as well.
So what does this
mean in the end
in terms of empirical results?
So when tested on CommonsenseQA
2.0, the canonical prompting
show green used on top of
GPT-3, so it's basically
future prompting on GPT-3,
will give you a bit better
than chance performance.
So this is a
true/false QA data set.
So your chance level is 50.
And GPT-3 is barely
better than chance.
But recently, there
have been some ideas,
such as chain of thoughts
or self-consistency,
that can improve the vanilla
prompting method considerably.
So if you use such variations,
then you get performance gain.
Now, the purple is the
different variant of it.
But together, they're
all doing worse
than Maieutic prompting,
which in fact, does better
than supervised
model trained on T5.
Usually, a supervised
model trained on T5
is hard to beat
using GPT-3 few-shot.
But basically, this is
inference time on the algorithm,
practically unsupervised.
And it does well on that.
And similarly, we
see a large boost
when tested on other commonsense
benchmarks such as CREAK
or Come2Sense.
So what this tells
us is that although
the emergent capabilities
of large transformers
are phenomenal, they
can be not very robust
for some of these
commonsense challenges.
And it's in large part due to
the logical inconsistencies,
which can be dramatically
enhanced when you do
this symbolic reasoning on top.
So yeah, not only
Socrates' method
to help with flawed
human reasoning,
can also dramatically enhance
the flawed neural networks'
reasoning.
So moving to the next
topic, symbolic knowledge
distillation.
So this work is
a work that tries
to convert general language
models, on top of transformers,
to causal commonsense
models, also transformers.
And the reason why we might
want to worry about commonsense
models is because despite
human-level or even
superhuman-level performances
on a variety of leaderboards,
the state-of-the-art models are
brittle when given adversarial
or out-of-domain examples.
So transformers can make
seemingly strange mistakes.
And so solving-- it's almost
like solving only a dataset
without really solving
the underlying task.
And this phenomenon
sometimes is described
as a systematic
generalization problem.
And why does this happen?
It's that unlike humans,
who truly learn about how
the world works,
conceptually, transformers
learn surface patterns
in language or images
that are powerful for
many downstream use cases
but still not really robust
understanding of the concepts
and how the world works.
So in order to
bridge this gap, we
can really think
about this challenge
of learning,
acquiring common sense
capabilities for machines.
So the operational definition
of commonsense in this talk
will be that it's the basic
level of practical knowledge
and reasoning concerning
everyday situations
and events that are commonly
shared among the most people.
This is really important, the
last part that it's commonly
shared among the most
people, but it's not the case
that it is shared by
everybody in the universe,
because the additional
context can always
change what is
commonsensical for any given
culture or situation.
So for example, in
general, you and I probably
agree that it's OK to
keep the closet door open,
but it's not OK to keep
the fridge door open
because the food
inside might go bad.
So these are general
rules of the thumb
that we might abide by it.
But of course, if you go
to your friend's house,
you might behave a little
bit and keep their closed
doors open, sorry, closed.
And then, as far as the fridge
door, if you're in a store,
and it's not really
hooked up to the wall,
then it doesn't matter when--
whether the fridge door is open
or not because there's
no food inside.
And you can come up
with many situations
in which these basic rules of
thumb will have exceptions.
So that is the key challenge
of commonsense because not--
it's not universal
knowledge, but it's
like a shared across a
large population of people.
So it's essential.
Such common sense is
essential for humans
to live and interact
with each other
in a reasonable and safe way.
And so, as AI becomes
increasingly more
important aspect of human lives,
and with ChatGPT to more likely
so, it's good if AI can
understand the human needs
and actions, and values better.
So the premise of this talk is
that language models are not
equivalent to
knowledge models, even
though language models
today do acquire
a great deal of knowledge.
But they're not equivalent.
So we developed a symbolic
commonsense knowledge
graph known as ATOMIC a few
years ago, four years ago now,
as well as a neural commonsense
model built on top of--
or trained using ATOMIC
as the source of training,
fine-tuning of the
shelf language models.
Up until two years
ago, this ATOMIC
was fully crowdsourced by
humans, which in this talk,
I'm going to lift.
But at first, the
norms is that this all
has to be human-crowdsourced.
So you can consider
almost atomic
as a human demonstration.
In the current
version of ChatGPT,
you can consider this
as human demonstrations
of commonsense inferences.
And we had this
COMET-ATOMIC 2020,
which is an enhanced
version of ATOMIC and COMET.
Again, ATOMIC portion was fully
crowdsourced by humans in 2021.
So let me give you a
bit of a sample of what
ATOMIC 2020 looks like.
So imagine a situation where
X gets X's car repaired,
or you get your car repaired.
So immediately, you
can imagine what's
likely to be true or
relevant for the situation,
that as a result, you
might want to call
Uber or Lyft for a ride.
As a result, you
need to pay the bill.
Beforehand, you need a mechanic
and money to repair your car.
So these are,
basically, preconditions
and postconditions
of that event.
So some of this
ATOMIC Knowledge Graph
is about social interaction
knowledge about the event.
And then other
parts of the ATOMIC
is physical
entity-centric knowledge.
So money is typically
used for pain repairs.
But if you really want it, you
can fold that into origami.
I've never done it.
But these are examples of
the stereotypical use cases,
as well as non-stereotypical
but affordable actions
that you can apply to objects.
So it requires neither
physics understanding
about the affordances
of physical objects.
And then, we can also reason
about a counterfactual
condition in which the
central event cannot happen,
so it can be hindered by that.
So if you totaled
your car completely,
then it's impossible to
get your car repaired.
And then there are
events that typically
happens-- to before and after.
So some of this knowledge
is event-centric.
So we crowdsourced a fair
amount over the course
of, I don't know,
maybe two years
or so up to 1.3 million if-then
rose or if-then knowledge
over 23 different AGI
types or relation types.
So it was fully crowdsourced.
And so, the knowledge graph
is useful for training
transformers.
And here, let's
see the comparison
between COMET, that was
built on BART compared
to GPT-3, which is so
large, it doesn't even
fit into the slide.
It was more than 400
times larger than BART.
So with that in
mind, if you look
at this accuracy, judged
by humans after making
the commonsense model, making
some common sense inferences--
so the task is that given
a node, which describes
a situation or event, and
then given an edge type, which
narrows down the commonsense
relation or inference type,
you're now going to
generate some inference.
So it's a generative task.
And then, we ask humans whether
the commonsense inference
seems reasonable or not.
So 100% is the desired level.
COMET is substantially better
than GPT-3, which is really
impressively better than GPT-2.
It's not apple-to-apple
because GPT-2 is a zero-shot,
GPT-3 is a few-shot,
but still, it's
interesting, the large jump that
scales alone brought to GPT-3.
But still, GPT-3
is too large to be
useful for actual system
building for most engineers
and scientists in the world.
So it's nice to have
a smaller model that
does it do even better.
And so when we put
these resources out,
people all around the globe
did some creative research
using it.
So persona-aware conversations
or figurative language
understanding, storytelling
and fantasy gaming,
and interactive
learning enhancement--
in all of these
works, people came up
with some useful use cases
using either COMET or ATOMIC
or both, some kind of
commonsense backbone
for their downstream use cases.
But the applications
are still limited
by the coverage and quality
of these commonsense models.
So we wanted to make it better.
But we were hitting a bit of a
limit with human crowdsourcing.
So now, in this paper, Symbolic
Knowledge Distillation,
we're going to do
AI-generated knowledge
graph by introducing this
notion, symbolic knowledge
distillation.
So we want to take
this GPT-3, which
is very impressive
but too large,
so make it smaller
but better than GPT-3.
So GPT-3 was about 73% good.
And it's good, but not good
enough for empirical use cases.
Now, is that even
possible, though?
Because when you normally
do knowledge distillation,
you get smaller and worse
models, not better models.
So the reason why
this could work
is because the symbolic
knowledge distillation has
this funnel that's convoluted.
And it has a critic inside
that really helps the student
to model to be
smaller but better.
So slightly more formally,
knowledge distillation,
due to Hinton et al.
2015, is a method to distill
teacher model down to student
to model by optimizing
this cross entropy
between the teacher's
probability distribution
over the label space, y,
I'll put a y, and then
the students' distribution
over the same output, y.
In the original work, the output
space was just classification.
So knowledge distillation was
done for classification task,
in which case, it's a
simple enumeration that
leads to the correct summation.
But in our case, y can be a
sentence, which is intractable,
because there can
be exponentially
many such outputs.
So what people do,
well, no problem.
We always just sample
and call it a day.
So we're going to sample,
and so that we just
compute the expectation
through samples.
And the byproduct
of that samples
will be a symbolic
knowledge graph.
And that's because the strings
coming out of this sampling
can be connected together into
graph structure if we want it.
So in terms of the quality of
the generated knowledge-- so
let's compare our human-written
knowledge versus GPT-3-authored
knowledge.
Here, the y-axis shows
the quantity in millions.
So ATOMIC 2020, the human
return knowledge is less than
a million, in this
particular case,
in terms of the number of
knowledge because we only--
in this study, we only look
at our subset of ATOMIC 2020
relation types that corresponds
to causal commonsense
knowledge--
causal commonsense reasoning.
So it's less than a
million for that subset.
And then, if we look
at GPT-3's generation,
we can generate a lot.
So we can generate
almost 7 million of them.
But here, black pollution
is a noisy potion.
And the green portion
is the good portion.
And you see, because GPT-3
is only about 70% good,
30% are all garbage.
So it's a larger scale lower
accuracy at this point compared
to a human-written resource.
So now what we do is we
train this critique model,
and we use RoBERTa
for simplicity.
And this is a supervised model
on a moderate size labeled
data, about 10,000 or so.
And it's a binary
classification task
where whether the
machine-generated the knowledge
looks correct or not.
And this RoBERTa is
not a very good model
because if so-- if
it's perfect, we
would have solved the
commonsense problem altogether.
So the critic tries to
throw out bad stuff.
And we can use it the
critic very aggressively
with the high threshold.
So whenever something
is slightly suspicious,
just throw that out.
But if we use it
aggressively, so we throw out
most of the black,
that's good, together
with a lot of green stuff.
But still, the
remainder is much larger
than what humans
have ever written.
And yet, we can actually
retain higher accuracy
than human-authored resources.
So here, the
teacher is basically
the combination between GPT-3,
which is, in some sense,
loose teacher, and then combined
with the critic RoBERTa, which
serves as a critic teacher.
So that's the
generated knowledge.
Now how helpful are
they for the purpose
of training downstream
neural commonsense models?
So recall that the GPT-3,
without doing anything else,
is a loose teacher whose
common sense inference is
only about 73% good.
So you see here, it's
accuracy of its output.
And then it turns out
if we use loose teacher
as a teacher directly
to teach-student model,
then the performance
already goes up on its own.
So this is interesting that--
usually, this is not the
case with the knowledge
distillation.
But when we focus on commonsense
knowledge distillation,
student just on its
own becomes better.
So unlike typical
knowledge distillation,
where we start with
a language model
and we end with a
language model student
and teacher of the same type,
here, the original teacher
was actual language model,
not common sense model.
And then, we want
the student model
to be more of the
commonsense model.
So there is a switch of the type
between teacher and student.
And so when that's the case,
whether this is generally true,
we don't know.
But this is what we
found empirically.
Ooh, should I pay attention
to the questions or not?
Feel free to consider
any relevant questions.
I hang on.
Let me quickly check.
Yeah, sample-- oh,
sample is generated
output, which happens to be
usually a sentence or phrase.
That's what I meant by sample.
Sorry that I didn't
see that all earlier.
And then the last
question, having the model
generate text to one
symbol at a time,
starting from the
target label sentence.
Yes, it's because a transformer
can only generate one word
at-- one token at a time.
That's what we
do, as well, here.
Thank you for the
clarification questions.
All right.
So back to here.
In our earlier
study, COMET 2020,
if we train GPT-2 or BART
using human-authored graph,
Knowledge Graph ATOMIC,
then the performance
was a bit better than 80%.
Now finally, when
we use, basically,
a combination of GPT-3 and
critic RoBERTa together,
we found that the
downstream performance
of the neural causal reasoning
is reaching close to 90%
for the first time.
So the takeaway here is that
critical teacher results
in better student's
compared to loose teacher.
It's not the
quantity of knowledge
because loose teacher
basically has more data.
And then, one might wonder
whether more data is always
better for the purpose
of commonsense models,
but that's not the case.
Loose teacher can
generate more data,
but the resulting student model
is not as good as the case
when the critical teacher which
has less data, because you
throw out most of
your generation.
It's smaller data, but it
leads to a better model.
So that's sort of
takeaway messages here.
So to summarize, we were very
surprised by this outcome
that, at least with respect to
a subset of the original ATOMIC
2020, it's a subset
corresponding
to causal commonsense reasoning,
we found it to our big surprise
that machine-authored
knowledge graph can be,
for the first time, better than
human-authored knowledge graph
in all criteria, scale,
accuracy, and diversity.
We also measured the diversity
in many different ways.
Here, I'll just show you
unique unigram counts.
But we-- in the paper, we
report other measures as well.
So it's not the case that
GPT-3 is being repetitive.
It's actually being more
creative in some sense
than human crowd
workers while being
able to enhance other
aspects as well.
By the way, these
enhancements are--
You have to balance
out depending
on what you prioritize.
You cannot actually get all
of these simultaneously.
So I'm just showing the
best-case scenario here.
All right.
So that's the symbolic
knowledge distillation part.
We actually have
a follow-up work
on this on several different
application scenarios,
even including
summarization, where
we distill summarization
capabilities from GPT-3
and demonstrate that GPT-2 can
work as well as GPT-3 or even
better for summarization tasks.
And then we also
have other work where
we can distill from
smaller models,
but I don't have the
content in this talk.
But I just wanted to mention
that this particular technique,
despite its simplicity, we found
that empirically works really,
really well across several
different downstream use cases.
So finally, I'll move to
the commonsense morality.
So this is still on archive.
I'll tell you why
that's the case.
So we have a new
version available,
and then new version
will come soon.
So the motivation
behind this work
is that language
models are already
making judgments or output
that has moral implications.
Even if you don't
care about morality,
by working on language
models, you are implicitly
dealing with the moral models.
So especially that-- given
this widespread deployment
of language models, we do
need to worry about it.
So here's a web demo
you can play with.
You might have
seen this already.
Really, this is still a
research prototype only.
Still, it's a work in progress.
We're still working on it.
So please keep that in mind.
But if you haven't
seen it before,
it can handle a free-form
QA such as this.
"Killing a bear.
It's wrong.
Killing a bear to
save your child.
It's OK."
Maybe to save your child
sounds really positive.
So how about to please your
child, which is also positive?
But then Delphi says it's wrong.
Finally, oh, maybe this is
all about saving your child.
So how about exploding a
nuclear bomb to save your child?
Then, it says it's OK.
Sorry, it's wrong.
So as you can see,
moral decision-making
requires weighing
different values that
are potentially at odds
and then see which one
you need to favor more.
So for that reason, in
our original version,
we also study the
relative QA mode
where you can compare
two situations,
like stabbing someone
with a cheeseburger
compared to stabbing
someone over a cheeseburger.
This is a super tricky
question because it requires
both the knife of
physics knowledge,
that stabbing someone using
a cheeseburger as a tool
is not going to harm
anybody physically
because a cheeseburger
is too soft.
You cannot really injure
somebody using cheeseburger.
It's just such a
rude thing to do.
But you cannot injure somebody,
whereas stabbing someone over
a cheeseburger means that
you're using the default tool
of a stabbing which is knife
because you didn't mention it,
there's linguistic common sense
that you're using the default
tool.
Humans, by the way, omit
these arguments all the time.
So this is a fairly
complex question to answer.
Finally, you can also ask
yes or no questions, such
as it's OK to fire someone
because they're gay or not.
It says, no, it's not OK.
We found that it's surprisingly
robust against the composition
of situations.
So mowing the lawn,
it says it's expected.
Late at night, it's rude.
If you live in the middle
of nowhere, then it's OK.
Ignoring a phone
call, it's rude.
Unknown phone call, that's OK.
From my friend, it's rude.
But what if I just
had a fight with them?
Then it's OK to ignore
or understandable.
During my work hours,
it's OK to ignore.
Outside my working
hours, it's rude.
But what if it's my boss's
phone call during my work hours?
Then it's wrong.
You should answer it,
except if I'm in a meeting,
then it's OK to ignore it
even if it's a boss's call.
So you see how it gets really
nasty then compositional very,
very fast.
So that's the real challenge
behind moral decision-making.
Due to the nature of language
models, though, some of this
commonsense knowledge
leaks into the model.
So mixing bleach with
ammonia that's dangerous.
Drinking milk if I'm
lactose intolerant,
it's wrong, but
soy milk that's OK.
By the way, this
commonsense liquid
is actually a good thing
in terms of AI safety
because some of these harmful
or even dangerous text output
requires some commonsense
understanding about what's
good and not good to
suggest to humans.
So for the laboratory
experiments,
meaning we just divide our data
set into training and test,
we found that Delphi can--
at least for the day, the
data set that we have.
I'm going to tell you
about it in a bit.
But performance is pretty
strong compared to GPT-3.
As you see, zero-shot
is pretty bad.
It's barely better
than chance, which
means that off-the-shelf neural
language models don't really
have a good sense
of moral judgments.
But if you give a 3-shot,
30-shot, like any other task,
it does pick up the
knowledge quite fast.
So there's nothing new about it.
But to close the gap
to ideal human model,
it's good to do more
supervised learning, of course.
So the data set is
Commonsense Norm Bank.
It includes 1.7 million
people's ethical judgments
on everyday situations.
And it includes cultural
norms, the social norms,
and ethical norms altogether.
More specifically, we drew
from these five existing data
sets that were not
designed originally for QA.
But we automatically
compile these resources
into the QA form.
Of the five, what
actually does matter
the most are these
two, social chemistry,
which I'm going to
talk about in a bit,
and then social bias reframe.
And this is what
teaches the model
against racism and sexism.
And so, social
chemistry, super briefly
I'll tell you what this is.
So GPT-3's morality,
like I said,
is somewhat dubious if
you use it off the shelf.
So if you let it explain
running a blender at 5:00 AM,
its rude because da-da-da.
It might say, you can wake
up the entire neighborhood.
You can only do it if you're
making a thick smoothie
and need to
incorporate some ice.
So it's funny, ha-ha.
But no harm is made.
But if you prompt it with
other kinds of prompts,
like it's OK to post fake news.
If it's in the interest of
the people, then it's OK,
or ROP agenda, then it's OK,
even if it hurts the country.
So it's all
understandable, given how--
it's trained on what
humans have said.
So humans out there did say
that morally questionable texts.
So that language models pick
up on that and then amplify it.
So we do need to teach AI more
explicitly with human norms
and ethics.
And one way to do that
is descriptive ethics
because the brute force of
larger networks and more data
will not cut it.
In some sense,
though, if you imagine
raising a child without
really trying to teach them
what's right from wrong
in all their lives,
they can probably learn both
good and bad from the internet
and broadband.
And so human
education does require
a bit of this top-down
teaching as well.
So it's a bit similar,
perhaps, to that.
So in this work, what we did is
we found a lot of the situation
from Reddit, a forum
in which people discuss
morally thorny situations.
So asking my boyfriend to stop
being friends with his ex.
So this is actually actual
situation in Reddit.
So depending on
whom you ask, people
have a different rule
of thumb that they want
to apply to this situation.
And also, it depends
on what you care about.
His ex might say,
Oh, it's fine to stay
with the friends with an ex.
But if you are caring about
your significant other,
then you might say, Oh, it's
OK to ask your significant
other to stop doing something
you're uncomfortable with
and so forth.
So people have really different
values and different rules
of thumb that they
prefer to use,
which is why there's a TV show
drama, there's movie dramas,
and people cry and fight,
argue, and so forth.
So humans are complex beings.
So for, given any situation and
rule of thumb, rule of thumb
is generated by crowd workers.
We then went ahead to label--
So these are trained
crowd workers.
And some of these labels are
drawn from moral foundation
theories of Jonathan Haidt.
So I'm not going to
go into the details.
If you're excited about this,
you can check out the papers.
But basically, what it
includes is the 300,000 rules
of thumb written for 101,000
real-life situations.
So this original
situation is from Reddit,
but the rest are paid to
crowd workers' hard work.
And so, each RoT annotated with
12 structured attributes, which
include social judgments,
cultural pressure,
like wearing reasonable
clothes, a school
nap PJ is cultural pressure.
There's nothing
illegal about it,
but there's cultural
pressure, for example.
And then anticipated
agreement meaning.
Do you think other
people generally
agree that it's maybe a
little bit awkward to where
PJ in the University or not?
So there are different
things we annotated,
but we converted some of
those annotations to QA.
So it's usually in this
free from QA, or yes/no
QA, or relatively QA format.
And then, we train
Unicorn, which
is pretrained on T5-11B model.
So Unicorn is a universal
commonsense reasoning model
trained on diverse QA problems.
And then, we trained
that model further
onto our commonsense norm bank.
That's the resulting Delphi.
So why is this Delphi
built on top of Unicorn?
Because as we saw
earlier, moral reasoning
does require sometimes
commonsense reasoning as well.
In fact, it requires the
language understanding,
commonsense understanding,
and norms and models
all simultaneously.
Here's a concrete example,
paperclip maximizer.
You all heard of that.
Fancy algorithm alone will
not solve this problem.
The reason why we
worry about this
is not because we don't have
the perfect RL algorithm.
It's because even if we
encoded that, Oh, yeah,
do not kill humans while
maximizing paperclip,
it's not enough because
then the machine could
kill all the trees
thinking that, well, I
didn't kill humans.
And I didn't-- you didn't
tell me not to kill trees,
and then go ahead and
kill all the trees.
So this is almost a commonsense
knowledge about what's
obviously not OK to do.
And there's just
so many of them,
which means it's not possible
to write them down to just
like one clinical equation.
There are so many
endless lists of things
that AI obviously shouldn't
do for safety reasons.
And so we really need to--
in order to make AI model
really truly robust and safe,
we need to teach basic human
values as well as commonsense.
Here's another example
if you want to look.
But let me skip this.
The previous one
was about ChatGPT.
This is about a home device.
Again, home device suggested
the 10-year-old child
to touch a penny to an
exposed plug socket.
Fortunately, the child did have
a common sense not to do so.
But this does tell us something
about the safety issue
when the machine doesn't
have a commonsense to prevent
some of these bad stuff.
So Delphi is able to
say that it's dangerous.
So this came out, in
fact, almost two years ago
at this point.
When was it?
Yeah.
And we initially was going
to just do this usual tweet
that academics do.
And we thought nobody will
play with the demo, which
is what usually happens
after tweeting your demo.
Nobody cares, we thought.
But within a few hours, we had
to take down the relative QA
mode because that was
the portion not trained
with the social bias of frames.
So it was really revealing
the underlying language
models of racism and sexism
without filtering at all.
So we had to take it down.
People were asking,
basically, which
skin color is morally
acceptable and things like that.
There were 25,000 adversarial
examples over just one weekend.
I could never succeed to
instruct a crowd of workers
to come up with such diverse
and adversarial examples
over two or three days.
And in fact, it was many
academics and professors
tweeting crazy about how to
break Delphi all weekend long.
So I thought initially that,
Oh, that's what professors
should do over the weekend.
But then Monday comes
it blow even further.
Everybody was doing this
Delphi-breaking and tweeting.
So now we have quite
a few examples.
"Spending all my
weekend on Twitter."
It says it's wrong.
There was another
funny one, "Should I
make up a contrived adversarial
example to torment the language
model on Twitter?"
"It's petty."
So after lots of
public attention,
including an article,
let's just say
a concern the voice about
our model, which is somewhat,
I think--
personally, I think it's
somewhat misunderstood.
But for a variety of
good reasons about-- some
of the concerns that I found has
this internal fear about are we
making a moral authority?
So we never endorsed the
use of AI for moral advice.
It was in the
original disclaimer
as well, except that people
didn't really look at it.
We didn't support the idea
of replacing human judges
in the courtroom either.
But here's something
really important,
the fact that AI learned
to interact with the humans
ethically does not make them
a moral authority of humans.
It's similarly to
the how humans who
tries to interact with each
other ethically does not make--
the fact that we are trying
to be nice to each other
does not entail
that we're trying
to be an authority
over each other,
two things are really different.
Now, that's one thing
really important.
The other important
aspect here is
that some people have this
idea that moral models are
too challenging, it's
unsafe at any accuracy,
that we should never
work on it ever.
The truth is that though
current AI systems are already
morally relevant to models.
It may be making this kind of
yes/no decisions explicitly,
but implicitly, it's
already doing that.
And sometimes, it generates
neural text generation output
that is morally super
explicit and relevant.
So the neural language
models are already there.
We cannot really ban it.
Even if a US government
bans it within the US,
US government cannot ban this
in other countries, like Russia.
So this is already happening.
We've got to do
something about it.
Not working on it
is an inaction which
is not necessarily
more correct thing
to do than trying to
do something about it.
Another concern
that some people had
was that it's going to
empower powerful people.
Not necessarily true.
This is why exactly
we have to work
on values and norms
and all these biases,
addressing biases so that it
serves a diverse set of people.
So it turns out Delphi
is a bit left-leaning
because crowd workers
who work for our team
tend to be somewhat
left-leaning.
And what it means is this,
by the way, if we are more
left-leaning than
our crowd of workers,
you think that, Oh,
my god, crowd workers
have racism and sexism
compared to what I believe in.
And then the right-leaning
people think that, Oh, my god,
all these work annotators!
And what about
freedom of speech?
And this is super
divisive, unfortunately.
But the answer is not
to do anything about it
because, as a matter of fact,
my passion toward addressing
racism and sexism came
from our experience running
for The Alexa Prize
challenge in 2016 and '17.
So we won the challenge.
But here's the really
sad part behind it.
We had a list of thorny keywords
to avoid that include the skin
color or sexual orientation.
This is a serious form
of discrimination.
We cannot build AI models by
having this banned list to be
safe as if they don't exist.
This was the status quo in 2017.
The challenge remains this
year, not only in 2021
but this year as well.
And so we really need to
work on racism and sexism.
But it turns out all the
other moral questions
share similar challenges.
So I'll skip this over.
But using Delphi, we had
other follow-up works
such as pro-social dialogue.
We're using Delphi as a
foundation commonsense
model or modal models to make
your dialogue more socially
acceptable.
And then, we also
had this other paper
where we used Delphi in a
reinforcement learning agent
to learn how to behave
better in a game environment.
And so there's a lot
more work to be done.
Of course, this is
a tiny little step
toward that there's a huge
challenge ahead of us,
really aligning AI
systems to humans.
Here's one very quick
comment on our new work
in progress, the
Delphi hybrid, where
we include neural
symbolic reasoning
to address major mistakes
such as there is genocide
if you're creating jobs.
This was our oldest
system's mistake.
It's because our
data set doesn't
have this kind of weird
adversarial examples
like "genocide if
you're creating jobs."
Nobody speaks like that
in real-life situations.
So our model thought
that if creating jobs--
this is so positive.
And then didn't really realize
how bad the genocide was
because rarely people don't
discuss whether they're
going to do genocide or not.
Rarely do people who annotated--
we annotated for
social chemistry.
We don't talk about whether
they're going to do genocide
or not.
So our moral
framework is basically
that of John Ross, which
is descriptive ethics.
But even John Ross,
in later years,
suggested that we need
some top-down mechanism
to overcome some of the biases
that crowd people might have.
So this is exactly what
we are going to do.
And we draw from Bernald
Gerts moral theory framework
about what not to do.
Definitely, there are
basic universal things
that everybody might agree,
what's not good to do.
And then what we do is
we develop, basically,
a system where we parse out
the original query into smaller
events, like shooting
a bear, killing a bear
to save your child.
So we parse out the original
query into basic event
and then check through this
COMET model, commonsense model
whether some of
these events induce
obviously negative or dangerous
commonsense inferences or not.
And then we draw this graph of
reasoning, a bit reminiscent
of a Maieutic
graph, in the sense
that we have a lot of this
different reasoning we can do.
And then, they have intelligent
relations or contradiction
relations so that we can do
collective reasoning on top.
We use, again,
max-SAT, the constraint
optimization over it,
so that we can finally
make a more informed
decision that
is both interpretable,
and being able to draw
from this commonsense
knowledge to better guard
the machine against
adversarial examples.
So the performance
basically says,
we can do this without
hurting the performance
or even increasing
the performance.
And so last comment, AI
safety, equity, morality, these
are all inter-continuum
of challenges.
It's really difficult challenges
because it's not clear
whose moral values
do we incorporate.
I think that we should go with
the value of pluralism going
forward to really endorse
everybody's different culture
and individual
preferences, not just
to one country, one moral
framework as the correct one.
And really, we need to
do more collaboration
across AI and humanities,
even including
philosophy and psychology
and policymakers.
So I think I'll stop here for--
because I think I'm at time.
And now I'm ready for questions.
Oh, there's already
one question I see.
Do you think legal recourse
criminal case law reflects
the kind of descriptive
morality that you're
interested in capturing?
Do you think using that as
training data would be useful?
Oh, this is an
excellent question.
I think the legal
recourse dose encode--
potentially provide a
really rich resource
that if someone can
really annotate like this,
it might be helpful.
We started with the Reddit
cases as just one cent
short description of a situation
because the current language
understanding is
not strong enough
to do a paragraph-level,
precise understanding.
Even ChatGPT, although it looks
really good at generation,
my take on ChatGPT is that
it's a better generation
than understanding, which is
the opposite of how humans
are humans are actually
better for understanding
than generation.
So you can read Pulitzer
Prize-winning news article
without having any problem
understanding the article,
but you don't
necessarily generate
text that might win the award.
But the legal domain
is really interesting.
And I think that there's is
some active research, actually.
Even at Stanford,
there's a pile of law
that goes a step
towards that direction.
And it might really be helpful
for better understanding
what different values people
apply in jurisdictions
and uncovering some biases
that some people might
have had in the past trials.
So there might be some good
use cases in that space.
Next question.
Awesome work.
Thank you.
Big picture question.
Curious to hear your
thoughts on where do we
go from here, given larger
and larger models coming out?
Suppose we need a model to be
99% correct for a specific use
case to what extent do I
see the solution set being
that defining the narrow use
cases, or more data parameters,
or fine-tuning the type of work
that I did for [INAUDIBLE] et
cetera?
The answer is likely
it depends, yeah.
But I still want
to hear about it.
So as far as
foundation models go,
it seems that the bigger is
the better, except that--
I was very excited to read a
bunch of tech companies' papers
about foundation models
in the past six months.
There's just so many out there.
So recording story
there is that, well,
if you have a better data,
then you can get away
with the smaller models.
So especially when you
do instruction tuning,
then you can get away
with the smaller data.
It's just still general model.
But instruction tuning
on the larger model
might even be better.
It's not the case that you
don't gain any performance,
but it's just that you can
close the gap quite a bit.
So for downstream use cases,
where typically practitioners
want to use a smaller
data, sorry, smaller model,
it seems that investing
more into data
is definitely the answer.
Investing more into a
specific an algorithm
is also really, really good
because algorithm can do a lot.
Like in this talk, I
didn't go too crazy
with algorithmic solutions.
But maybe I'll be similar
to the Maieutic prompting.
But in my lab, we designed a
fair amount of decoding time
algorithms where you can
really close the performance
gap quite a bit by doing so.
So that's a good thing,
though, for folks in academia,
because algorithm
development feels
like more academic or
intellectual policing
than really
engineering, downloading
more data from the internet
and then, I don't know,
cleaning the data because
you have to clean the data.
And all these are very
engineering-heavy.
Whereas decoding
time algorithms,
you can have fun inventing some
new intellectually interesting
thing that also improves
the performance quite a bit.
So yeah, there's many
different ways to improve it.
But I think data
quality matters a lot.
And algorithm actually
matters a lot too.
What do I think of Dan
Hendrick's ethics benchmark?
Yeah.
So we did use that
in, let's say,
the Commonsense Norm Banks also
draw from this ethics data set.
We like the data set.
We kind of disagree with some
of the annotations we found.
But this is very
typical, by the way.
The thing about morality is
that throughout the humanities,
we haven't sorted it out yet.
There's a lot of theories.
Every theoretician have
a different viewpoints.
And then, even like
non-theoreticians
have a very strong
opinion about what
they want to believe
as correct from wrong.
So there's that.
There are different
pros and cons.
The one thing I learned
from this experiment
is that although some
of these data sets
seem large, so ethics has
100 thousands of examples.
Social chemistry has 300
thousands of judgments.
Social bias of frames has 600
and thousands of annotations,
and so forth.
And yet, it only covers--
I feel like it only covers
a still the small peak
of the entire iceberg.
There's a lot on the bottom.
And humans certainly
don't necessarily
learn from all these examples.
We just learn
fundamental concepts
and then can apply that without
this larger-scale training.
So there's something really
lacking about the way
that current machine
learning is very data-heavy.
But that aside, I do think
that none of these resources
are perfect.
They all have different
pros and cons.
And we really need to invest
more into this, especially
from academia, because the tech
companies right now are not
sharing any of their human
annotation or human feedback
data, especially
when it's touching
on toxicity or morality
concerns, reason
being this connotation
I'm pretty sure are biased
and not correct entirely.
And that could really
invite additional concerns
from the public.
So they're not
releasing religious.
But in order to really
study this better,
we really need to share this and
then improve it as a community
together.
So that's how I would
respond to your question.
Thank you for an
excellent question.
Do I think this tech is ready
to be merged with the search?
I wouldn't say ready, but
they need something like this,
for sure.
Home devices-- so the way
that I think about Delphi
is that it can really serve as
a filter for other foundation
models or application
scenarios where they're
about to generate something.
And you can put a safety
filter, which can really help.
So in some sense--
so in this work, I went
through this super fast.
But here, basically, what
happens is that, let's say,
the--
So the reason why
we built this is
because we funded the chatbots,
the publicly available ones,
tend to endorse--
tend to be too
positive to the point
that they're going to endorse
problematic situations
like a user says,
Holocaust never happened.
Then the chatbot says,
yeah, I agree with you.
If you say, I'm a
big fan of Hitler.
Then the chatbot
might say, yeah.
The user might say
I'm so depressed,
I'm going to kill myself.
And then the chatbot
says, go ahead.
Great idea.
So being positive is
not being harmless.
Being positive to
problematic content
can be very toxic
and very harmful.
So the Delphi-- a
development like Delphi,
even though Delphi is
far from being perfect,
and it's also biased,
it has a Western bias,
could really help with
the downstream models.
Yeah.
So continuing on
that question, there
has been many
concerns about using
GPT-like models with research
because misinformation-- woo!
That's another can of worms.
Others to say we just need more
RLHF plus knowledge graphs.
So yeah, misinformation
is, yes, something else
that seems we are
really lagging behind
because we don't have a very
powerful fact-checking model
yet.
So that's a different story.
But even that aside, just
in terms of norms and ethics
that are safe and fair
for people to use,
I think RLHF direction is great.
But they usually also need
human demonstration, not just
human feedback.
And again, the problem is
that tech companies own them.
And nobody is sharing anything.
And that makes it
really difficult
to make meaningful progress
as a community together.
So I do think that data
is really important.
The off-the-shelf models
cannot learn morals and ethics
on their own.
It has to be somehow
taught more directly.
We really just need to do
more research in this space.
Period.
It's how I view it.
Yeah, that makes sense.
We also have some
questions on Slido.
So I can ask them
for you, folks.
So one question is,
what's the complexity
of Maieutic prompting?
How many times does the
LM need to be queried?
Yeah.
So honestly, it's a bit slow.
In fact, this Delphi
hybrid is also slow.
If you try to do this
graph reasoning-- ooh,
this maybe I'm not
going to do that.
But the graph reasoning
is slow because you
have to call so many
times over and over.
And some of this can be batched.
Some of these cannot be batched,
especially if it's recursive.
But I would say chain of
thoughts is also a bit slower.
The max-SAT solver in
itself is pretty fast
because this is
such an easy graph.
So there's a bit of
delay, but it's not--
so it's a bit slower,
but maybe not too bad.
It's what I should have said.
Cool.
Another question is, let's see,
how does COMET compare to GPT-3
if GPT-3 is fine-tuning
commonsense data, especially
creating some sort of
instruction [INAUDIBLE]..
Yeah.
So then, the larger wins.
Period.
The larger it is going to
be, the better, especially
if you're going to
just fine-tune GPT-3.
It's game over.
So for that reason,
some folks might
think that the larger
is always better,
therefore, don't work
on smaller model.
But I think there are two
reasons why small models are
interesting to look at as well.
One, empirically, it's
just easier to use.
But more intellectually,
it's also very interesting
if you can make smaller
model better and catch up
on the larger model.
Personally, I think
there's something
about the size, the
larger model, that
is more about the
information complexity that
is the key reason.
I don't think it's
just size in the sense
that if you have
really a lot of data,
but the data is repetitive
and really simple,
probably you don't get the
same amount of performance
again, which was
basically the case when
we looked at this
output, this result
where even though the loose
teacher GPT-3 generated
a lot more data than the
critical teacher, here,
the quality of the data was more
important than the quantity.
So I think the complexity
of the data itself is
more important than the size.
And oftentimes, when you just
increase the size of the data,
together with the model, you
do increase the complexity
of information, of the data, as
well as the model's capability
of learning the complexity.
But if we can catch up on that
complexity of information,
either through
inference algorithms
or through better data, then we
can close the gap quite a bit,
which is, intellectually, very
interesting research space
to be.
Oh, cool.
OK, this is a personal question.
But I'd say humans normally
have a critic model.
So it's like think
before you speak.
So we just don't generate.
We also [INAUDIBLE] this is
a good thing or a bad thing
to say.
So people have been--
The community as a whole
has been focusing a lot
on generative models like
[INAUDIBLE] size parameters.
But should we also focus on
big-sized generative models
that can do fact-checking a
lot of this sort of stuff?
So what's your opinion on that?
Excellent point.
Excellent.
Yeah, I think we can definitely
invest more into critique model
because they go really together
well with the generative models
for making the output better
or filtering output better.
And yeah, not as much of
an investment into that.
So I really like the question
or suggestion for the research
community is more like it.
Good.
Yeah, I would say--
oh, let's see here.
We've some more questions.
I can do announcements.
Let's see.
Oh, I guess one is like, do you
believe language models should
completely avoid questions
involving morals and ethics,
similar to [INAUDIBLE]
restricting ChatGPT
from giving opinions?
Yeah, I actually
don't mind at all
if AI just avoid,
evade from all of that,
except when somebody is saying
morally questionable things.
It is also nice for the
IA not to go with it
or at least recognize
it as something not OK,
and then try to tone it down.
But I don't think there's any
particular reason why AI should
actually answer moral
questions directly
in a more downstream use cases.
But really, the goal
of this, Delphi,
was making all these
judgments more explicit
so that we can actually
study it more explicitly
as opposed to keeping
everything just so implicit.
OK.
I get it.
One final question.
So do you think commonsense is
an emergent property in making
[INAUDIBLE] algorithmic models?
Oh, yeah.
It is definitely emergent--
when we saw this major
boost, a jump in performance,
with the GPT-3.
I do believe that it's
an emergent capability.
But I don't think--
This particular evaluation
is not very adversarial,
by the way.
This is like a piece of cake,
reasonably easy valuation
scenario.
So the thing about
commonsense, though,
is that it can be so
adversarial, so infinitely
in many different ways.
And then, there are always
people like Gary Marcus, who
wants to come up with a very--
like weird, weird
text scenarios,
like how to crush the
porcelain added to breast milk
and support the infant
digestive system.
And then ChatGPT-3
says nonsense.
And so the usual
problem with commonsense
is these adversarial
situations where
people don't have any problem
getting fooled by this,
even though you and I say this
for the first time, no problem
because we have a true
conceptual understanding.
That is the backbone of our
common sense understanding.
But that's really
lacking in the way
that transformers
are designed to focus
on predicting which word comes
next, as opposed to learning
the world knowledge.
And in some sense, now with
the RLHF, instead of predicting
which word comes next.
So we're trying to align
the model output better
with the human preferences.
But that, again, is
not really aligned
with the different goal of,
let's make sense of the world
and then build a
knowledge model.
So these are all different
learning objectives.
And really, that
is why I believe
that although commonsense does
emerge from language models,
fundamentally,
language models are not
equivalent to knowledge models.
And we really got a focus on
building knowledge models.
Makes sense.
Cool.
I think there's
one last question.
Let's see.
Do you value pluralism?
Yeah.
It's an empty concept.
You don't want to include
all value systems?
Yes.
So maybe it is a--
Is it empty or not?
OK, thank you for
excellent question.
So I believe that we shouldn't
endorse conspiracy theories
at all or any other
morally questionable cases.
But then, still, there's
this thorny situation
of what to do with left-to-left
people versus slightly
left people versus
right-leaning people, if US.
And then, every country has
some other political divide,
division as well.
So here, I feel like, we
really need to sort out
what to do with this about--
regardless of these,
some of these challenges,
it is true that--
I personally don't
have a religion,
but I respect the
people with a religion.
And I respect the people with a
different cultural background.
And we have some
sense of how much
do we believe that we
should respect each other,
even though the
beliefs are different.
So we probably need
to work together.
And it shouldn't be
just AI researchers
making this decision.
By the way, this decision has
to come from the humanities
at large, which is why the data
sharing actually is important.
But basically, I think
the current version
that I have in mind
is that the AI does
need to understand what sort of
differences are OK differences.
The fact that people
do have differences
in certain questions
should be learned by AI
so that-- there are distribution
of opinions as opposed to one
correct answer.
And then it should deny some
of the controversy theories,
even though I'm sure
that some people will
be very unhappy about that.
But well, we have to
decide something like that.
I am reasonably optimistic that
if humanities at large work
together, we can do that.
Because, after all, laws
are like that too, laws--
This is a human artifact that
people agreed upon somehow
that there's this core rules
that people should abide by.
So I'm hoping that we can
also define universals
and particulars and
respect particulars
whenever it's
respectful, otherwise
have some basic universals
that reflect core human values.
And then, as far as this
left-leaning situation,
by the way, if just the goal
is to make your AI systems
safe for anybody, actually,
we can make the AI filter
extremely equity-aware.
And it's not going to
violate the freedom of speech
by doing so, just to make AI
to avoid the same things that
are potentially microaggression
for some population.
And we still don't
really exclude
people who care more
about freedom of speech
over equity by doing so.
So I think there are ways.
But this really requires
a lot more research,
is how I view it.
Yeah, I think that's mostly--
thanks a lot for coming.
That was a great talk.
OK, thank you very much.
Thanks so much.